Guide to the Katharine F. Lenroot Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Writings and Speeches, 1911-1973
  - Subseries I.5: Writings-- By Burton Jesse Hendrick, 1928-1940s
    This subseries contains the original hand-written and typed manuscripts, and research notes of Burton Jesse Hendrick, three-time Pulitzer winner, and author of The Life of Andrew Carnegie. The materials here relate to the biographies of Andrew Carnegie and his wife Louise Whitfield Carnegie. In writing these biographies, Hendrick was financed by Mrs. Carnegie, but his connection with Lenroot is unknown.
    - “Benefactors of Andrew Carnegie”--Manuscript, 1930s (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Life of Andrew Carnegie
      - Original Manuscript1930s, (9 folders) (Box 13, Folder 2 to 10)
      - Original Manuscript, 1930s, (7 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 7)
      - Research Notes, 1928, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Louise Whitfield Carnegie Research Notes, 1940s (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Series II: Professional, 1924-1974
  This series contains materials from Lenroot's professional career, spanning five decades from the mid-1920s to the mid-1970s. Lenroot's earlier research, at the Wisconsin Industrial Commission and at the Children's Bureau, are included in the preceding series.
  - Subseries II.1: Biographical--Chronological, 1934-1972
    This subseries contains newspaper clippings and journal articles about Lenroot, and official biographical notes prepared by the Children's Bureau.
    - Biographical Notes Prepared by the United States Children’s Bureau, 1934-1960 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Clippings and Articles about Lenroot, 1934-1967, (13 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 3 to 15)
    - Who’s Who of American Women-- Correspondence, Manuscript, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-- Women Builders of Social Welfare, 1972, (5 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Subseries II.2: United States Children’s Bureau, 1924-1970
    Included in this subseries are articles, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, and photographs relating to the Children's Bureau and its projects. Also present are Lenroot's personnel files, including files of her promotion to Chief. Although Lenroot officially retired from the bureau in 1951, she maintained contact with the staff, exchanging opinions and advice, and the subseries also includes materials after her retirement.
    A significant amount of material in this subseries is regarding the White House Conference on Children in a Democracy in 1940 and the Mid-century White House Conferences in 1950, which Lenroot considered to be one of her major projects. Included are articles, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, photographs, proceedings, and speeches associated with the conferences. Another subject in this subseries is Lenroot's concern about the place of the Children's Bureau, which appears frequently in her correspondence.
    - Correspondence
      - General--Indexed, 1937-1941, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Abbott, Grace 1932-1939, (5 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 3 to 7)
      - American Academy of Pediatrics, 1951 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - American Red Cross, 1923 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Eliot, Martha, 1938-1947 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Mayo, Leonard, 1943-1946, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 11 to 12)
      - Perkins, Frances, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Puschner, Emma, 1928-1945 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Shaffer, Alice, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - University of Pennsylvania, 1922 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - White House-- King and Queen of England--Visit, 1939 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Photographs
      - Infant Care Twenty-five Millionth Copy of --Lenroot Inscribing, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Portraits of Lenroot, 1930s-1940s (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Reorganization
      - Federal Security Agency--Transfer from Department of Labor to
        - Edith Abbott Emergency Committee to Save the Children’s Bureau, 1946-1949, (3 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 9 to 10)
        - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Reorganization, 1956-1962, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 12 to 13)
      - Reorganization, 1965-1970, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 14 to 15)
    - Special Projects
      - Mid-century
        - National Committee for Children and Youth, 1950-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 16 to 17)
        - White House Conference on Children and Youth--Proceeding, Pamphlets, Photographs, 1949-1950, (4 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Social Security Amendment, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - White House Conference on Children in a Democracy, 1939-1943, (4 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 6 to 9)
    - Staff (Box 273)
      - Lenroot’s Appointment as the Chief
        - Certificate of Appointment Signed by President Roosevelt, 1934-1935 (Box 273)
        - Clippings, 1934 (Box 19, Folder 10)
        - Congressional Record, 1935 (Box 19, Folder 11)
        - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 19, Folder 12)
        - Correspondence, 1934-1935, (4 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Lenroot’s Personnel Record, 1935-1950 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Retirement and Death of, 1964-1970 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II.3: International Activities, 1924-1974
    Both during and after her service at the Children's Bureau, Lenroot was concerned with international and inter-American child welfare, and this subseries contains documents and photographs associated with the Pan-American Child Congresses, the League of Nations, and the United Nations and UNICEF. The subseries also includes Lenroot's own account of the history of the Children's Bureau's international activities.
    - Inter-American Child Welfare Work--Bulletins and Articles, 1939-1943 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace, 1945 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - International Social Welfare Fortnight, 1928 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - League of Nations--Advisory Committee on Social Questions--Photograph, late 1930s (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Pan American Child Congress
      - Fourth, 1924 (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - Fifth--Report and Bulletin, 1926-1927 (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Sixth--Report and Photographs, 1930 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Eighth, 1942 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Ninth, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - South America--Visit to, 1943, (3 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 4 to 6)
    - France--Visit to, 1945 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - UNICEF Executive Board--Resignation from, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - United Nations Temporary Social Commission--Photographs, 1946 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - United States Children’s Bureau
      - “International Activities of the Children’s Bureau”--Manuscript and Correspondence, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - History of International Activities, 1970-1974, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 11 to 12)
  - Subseries II.4: Special Events, 1930-1961
    Throughout her professional career, Lenroot received a number of awards and honorary degrees. Certificates, clippings, correspondence, and photographs relating to the awards and ceremonies constitute this subseries. Materials from her retirement from the Children's Bureau in 1951 provide an overview of her official career and the network she built in the course.
    - Honorary Degrees
      - Boston University, 1952, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 13 to 14)
      - Russell Sage College, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - Tulane University, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 16)
      - University of Wisconsin, 1938 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Western Reserve University, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Honorary Memberships and Awards
      - Academia Nacional de Medicina, 1930 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Albert Lasker Award--Awarded to Children’s Bureau, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - American Orthopsychiatric Association, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - American Swedish Historical Foundation, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - American Woman’s Association, 1948 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Brazil--Medal From, 1950 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Child Welfare League of America, 1951 (Box 273)
      - Church Federation of Los Angeles, 1942 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Church in the Gardens, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 10)
      - Council for Social Action of the Congregational Christian Churches, 1948 (Box 22, Folder 11)
      - Escuela Argentina de Asistentes Sociales, 1941 (Box 273)
      - Federation of Jewish Philanthropies, 1946 (Box 22, Folder 12)
      - Fraternal Order of Eagles, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - General Federation of Women’s Clubs, 1941 (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Hospitals and Homes of the Methodist Church, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 15)
      - Instituto Americano del Niño, 1962-1963 (Box 22, Folder 16)
      - Instituto Cultural Joaquín V. González, 1944 (Box 273)
      - Instituto Nacional del Niño--Peru,1943 (Box 22, Folder 17)
      - International Society for the Welfare of Cripples, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 18)
      - Labor News Review, 1948 (Box 22, Folder 19)
      - Museo Social Argentino, 1943 (Box 22, Folder 20)
      - National Institute of Social Sciences--Gold Medal, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 21)
      - Sociedad Boliviana de Pediatria, 1944 (Box 22, Folder 22)
      - Sociedad de Puericultura de Buenos Aires, 1941 (Box 22, Folder 23)
      - %tb %te Aw Survey rd, 1950, (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 24 to 25)
      - Ted Malone and %tb %te Ma Best Years azine, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 26)
      - University of Chicago--Rosenberger Medal, 1942 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Wisconsin Academy of Sciences, Arts, and Letters, 1947 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - United States Children’s Bureau
      - Fiftieth Anniversary, 1960-1963, (3 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 3 to 5)
      - Lenroot--Twenty-fifth Anniversary, 1940 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Retirement From
        - Biographies--Lenroot and Martha Eliot, 1951 (Box 23, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence--Bound by the Children’s Bureau, 1951 (Box 23, Folder 8)
        - Correspondence--Filed Alphabetically by the Children’s Bureau, 1951, (5 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 1 to 5)
        - Correspondence, Clippings, and Articles, 1951, (3 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 6 to 8)
        - Correspondence, Clippings, and Articles, 1951, (7 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 1 to 7)
        - Clippings--Filed by the Children’s Bureau, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 8)
        - Distinguished Civil Service Award, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 9)
        - Lenroot Scholarship Fund, 1952-1954 (Box 25, Folder 10)
        - Photograph--Signed by President Truman and Other Officials, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 11)
        - Resignation Letter to President Truman, 1951 (Box 25, Folder 12)
        - Testimonial Dinner
          - General, 1951, (2 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 13 to 14)
          - Photographs, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 1)
          - Speech, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1928-1973
  This series contains Lenroot's personal and professional correspondence unrelated to the Children's Bureau. Two folders of previously catalogued correspondence are included in this subseries. Correspondence directly associated with the Children's Bureau can be found in Series II: Professional. The correspondence in this series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Previously Catalogued Correspondence, 1938-1968, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 3 to 4)
  - General--Greeting Cards, 1963-1967 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Baine, Katherine, 1961 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Charnow, Anne, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Columbia University--on Katharine Lenroot Papers and Emma O. Lundberg Papers, 1960 and 1976 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Cleveland, Harlan, and President Kennedy, 1961 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Faegre, Christopher R., 1971 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Fisher, Elizabeth, 1964 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Geist, Carol Berg, 1971 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Hedgeman, Anna Arnold, 1950 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Hall, Heren--Henry Street Settlement, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Hobbs, Helen, 1966 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Larson, Garnet, 1966 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Lenroot, Arthur, 1928 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - Lenroot, Irvine, 1931-1944 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Leslie, Anita, 1969. (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - Lesser, Arthur, 1965-1973 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - Levinson, Margit, 1961 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - Mayo, Leonard, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - Nichols, Irvine L., 1969-1970 (Box 26, Folder 23)
  - Paulson, Belden, 1967-1969 (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - Plant, James C., 1937-1947 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - Rutgers University--Graduate School of Social Work, 1964-1968 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - State of New Jersey--Board of Child Welfare, 1963-1967 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - Van Horn, Abram, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - Zapoleon, Marguerite W., 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 29)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 1909-1973
  This series consists of subject files labeled by Lenroot, with the exception of the last subseries labeled during processing. In order to maintain the original context, this series has been separated from other series, but most of the subject matter relates to Lenroot's professional career, and the series includes printed materials, clippings, photographs and correspondence as well.
  - Subseries IV.1: Individuals, 1925-1973
    Many folders in this subseries include correspondence with, articles, and clippings about, or publications by the individual.
    - Abbott, Edith, 1947 and 1957 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Abbott, Edith and Grace, 1930s-1940s (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Abbott, Grace, 1925, 1939 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Addams, Jane, 1935-1936, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Addams, Jane--Hall of Fame Centennial, 1967-1968, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 6 to 7)
    - Araos, Maria Rosario, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Atkinson, Mary Irene--Photograph, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Bain, Katharine and Melvin R. Laird, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Blackburn, Cleo W.--Correspondence, 1952 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Branscombe, Martha, 1954-1966 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Breckinridge, S.P., 1948 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Brown, Josephine C., 1936-1942 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Canine, J.R., 1970 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Castendyck, Elsa, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Charnow, Anne, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Cohen, Wilbur--Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Cortese, Carla--Correspondence, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Curry, Ida, 1950, 1964-1965, (4 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Daily, Edwin F., 1970 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - DelliQuadri, Frederick, 1969-1970 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Eliot, Martha May, 1962-1969 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Enochs, Elisabeth Shirley, 1963-1966 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Franco, Persio--Correspondence, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Gomez Tejera, Domingo--Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Gravinska, Wanda, 1948, 1959, (2 Folders) (Box 28, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Hanlan, Archie--Paper by Hanlan about Lenroot and Aid for Dependent Children--Correspondence about the Paper, 1964-1973 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Harper, C.A., 1938 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Harrington, Polly and Belden Paulson, 1966-1968 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Kelley, Florence, 1955-1956 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Klein, Philip--Correspondence, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - LaFollette, Fola and Mary LaFollette--Correspondence, 1960, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Lathrop, Julia--Correspondence, 1924, 1931-1932 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Lesser, Arthur--Correspondence, 1968, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - McConnell, Beatrice--Correspondence, 1962 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - McHugh, Rose--Tribute by Lenroot, 1953 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Middleton, George--Correspondence, 1960 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Muhlbach, Christine--Correspondence, 1968 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Murphy, Prentice--Tribute by Lenroot, 1936 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Oettinger, Katherine B.--Correspondence, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Parker, Graham--Correspondence, 1966 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Pate, Maurice, 1965 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Perkins, Emily, circa 1950 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Perkins, Frances, 1953 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor--Correspondence, 1946 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Roche, Josephine--Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Ross, Elizabeth, 1954 and undated, (2 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 15 to 16)
    - Salcedo, Manuel F.--Correspondence, 1970 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Saunders, Richard P., 1960s, (2 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 18 to 19)
    - Smith, Delafield--Correspondence, 1956 (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Snow, William F., 1950 (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Theis, Sophie--Tribute by Lenroot, 1957 (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Trimble, Elizabeth, 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Vajkai, Julia--Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Whitton, Charlotte, 1952 (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Wiley, Alexander--Correspondence, 1953 (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Witte, Edwin, 1957 (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Witte, Ernest, 1966 (Box 29, Folder 28)
  - Subseries IV.2: Subjects and Organizations, 1912-1970
    These subject files often contain the organization's publications, sometimes accompanied by Lenroot's comments. Correspondence with Lenroot, research notes, including clippings and reprints, and papers written by Lenroot organization also appear in this subseries.
    - American (National) Association of Social Workers, 1953, 1956 (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - American Public Welfare Association, 1955-1960, (3 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 30 to 32)
    - Arthur Lehman Counseling Service, 1967, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 33)
    - Child Welfare League of America, 1955 (Box 29, Folder 34)
    - Child Welfare League of America, 1970 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Child Welfare Laws--Maternal and Child Welfare Act of 1945 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Children’s Charters, 1942 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Children and Defense, 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Community Development Foundation, 1960-1968 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Conference on Better Care for Mothers and Babies--Program, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Delta Kappa Gamma Society, 1966 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Family Assistance Plan--Clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Federal Aid, 1958 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - General Council Congregational and Christian Churches, 1954 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Indian Institute of Culture, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - International Children’s Institute, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - International Union for Child’s Welfare
      - “Future Role of the International Union for Child Welfare and Its Members,” 1956 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      - Geneva Conference--Correspondence, Photographs, 1955-1956 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      - “United Nations Aid to the Developing Countries,” 1961-1962 (Box 30, Folder 15)
      - United States Committee, 1960-1961 (Box 30, Folder 16)
      - United States Committee--Dissolution, 1967 (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - League of Nations--Advisory Committee on Social Questions, 1937 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Loyalty Investigation, 1948 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Mexican Border Project--United States Children’s Bureau, 1951 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Mother’s Pension Movement,1969 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches
      - Annual Meeting, 1958 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Migrant Report, 1965 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - National Association of Social Workers, 1960-1967, (4 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 6 to 9)
    - National Citizens Committee--“Children in the Democracy for Which We Serve,” 1942 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - New Jersey Citizens Committee, 1961 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Society--University of Wisconsin, 1912 (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Public Welfare--Report of Advisory Council, 1966 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Save the Children Foundation, 1960, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 14 to 15)
    - Social Security Act--Proposed Expansion, 1942 (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Social Security Reserve, 1962 (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Study of the Capacity of the United Nations Development System, 1969-1970 (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Teachers’ Strikes, 1967 (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - UNICEF
      - Contract as Consultant, 1962-1963 (Box 31, Folder 20)
      - Correspondence, 1962, 1966 (Box 31, Folder 21)
      - Field Manual--Drafted by Lenroot, 1963, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 22 to 23)
      - Loyalty--Criticism of UNICEF by the American Legion, 1958-1959 (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - National Social Welfare Assembly, 1959-1960 (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - “United Nations Aid to the Developing Countries for Extending and Improving Their Services for Children and Youth,” 1961-1962 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Vietnam War--Letters to The New York Times and The Trenton Times, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Wayne University Family Life Program, 1953 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - War Refugee Problems, 1938-1940, 1954 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - White House Conferences on Child Welfare, 1946 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IV.3: Personal--Chronological, 1909-1971
    This subseries holds a small collection of documents and photographs related to the personal life of Lenroot. The earliest material is from her high school years, and the latest dates from her eightieth birthday.
    - High School--Superior Normal--Commencement Program, 1909 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - University of Wisconsin--Commencement Program, Photographs, 1912 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook--Gift to Lenroot from John Prentice Murphy, 1935 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Washington House--Sale of, 1951 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Birthday--Eightieth--Luncheon at UNICEF--Speech, Correspondence, Photographs, 1971, (2 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 12 to 13)